Guide to the Jim Grimsley Papers, 1970-2018 and undated RL.00483
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jim Grimsley papers
1970-2018 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Grimsley, Jim, 1955-
RL.00483
19.75 Linear Feet
Collection includes Grimsley's personal journals, personal and professional correspondence, handwritten notebooks containing the creative beginnings of his novels and plays, drafts of of his writings, publicity, reviews, and publications by or about him in small magazines. Also includes published copies and translations of his writings.
Access Restrictions
As of 3/25/2016, all papers are open to use.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Purchased in 1997; additions received 2002, 2015, and 2019.
Accessions described in this guide: 1997-0055; 2003-0041; 2015-0153; 2016-0001; 2019-0050.
Biographical Note
Jim Grimsley is an author from Rocky Mount, NC, currently residing in Atlanta, GA.
Collection Overview
Collection contains personal journals (1973-1993); personal and professional correspondence (1970s-2018); handwritten notebooks containing the creative beginnings of his novels and plays; datebooks and appointment journals; writing drafts (1970s-2016); published copies and galleys of his works, including translations; publicity, reviews, and publications by or about him in periodicals. Topics in his writings include family violence, homosexuality, the lives of young boys, racism and desegregation, and growing up in the Southern United States. The collection includes materials from all stages of Grimsley's creative process for his many plays, short stories, articles, and books. Grimsley's papers also include a significant amount of material from his work as an author of speculative and science fiction, including drafts of essays and books, editorial correspondence, and documentation of his participation in science fiction conventions.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- 20th century -- United States; Boys -- United States -- Fiction; Gay men's writings, American; Gay authors -- Correspondence; Gay men in literature; Gay men -- Fiction; Southern States -- Fiction; Homosexuality and literature; Family Violence -- United States -- Fiction; North Carolina -- Fiction; Science fiction; Homosexuality and literature; Family Violence -- United States -- Fiction; Southern States -- Fiction; Science fiction
- Accession (1997-0055)
  - Journals (Box 1)
    - 1973-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Personal (Box 2)
    - Personal (Box 3)
    - Other correspondence, ca. 1982-1996 (Box 4)
  - Notebooks (Box 5)
    - 23 volumes (Box 5)
    - 19 volumes (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts (Box 7)
    - A- Dream Boy (Box 7)
    - Dream Boy-H (Box 8)
    - I-M (Box 9)
    - M-P (Box 10)
    - R- Winter Birds (Box 11)
    - Winter Birds-Y (Box 12)
  - Publicity (Box 13)
    - Printed Materials (Box 13)
    - Clippings (Box 13)
    - Videotapes (Box 13)
    - Printed Materials (Box 14)
- Accession (2003-0041)
  - Appointment books, 1980s (Box 15)
  - Personal correspondence, 1992-2000 (Box 15)
  - Personal correspondence, 1982-2001 (Box 16)
  - Journal, 1977-1978 (Box 16)
  - Asimov's Science Fiction (Box 17)
    Scope and Contents note
    Issues include Grimsley stories.
    Scope and Contents
    Oct./Nov. 2000 issue (2 copies), Mar. 2002 issue
  - Un Largo Camino (Box 17)
    Spanish translation of Comfort and Joy; Editorial Egales, 2001.
  - Hebrew translation of Comfort and Joy, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Kirith Kirin (Box 17)
    Advanced reading copy, bound upside-down; Meisha Merlin, 2000.
  - Boulevard typescript, with editing marks (Box 17)
  - Winter Birds typescript (partial) (Box 18)
  - Drag Queens of the 21st Century script rewrite, 1994-1995 (Box 18)
  - Mr. Universe play galleys, 1993 (Box 18)
  - Men's Style, Dec. 1995 (Box 18)
  - American Theatre, Sept., Nov. 1990, Jan., Apr., Oct. 1991 issues (Box 18)
  - Copies of introductions to Grimsley's work by Kaye Gibbons and Craig Lucas, 1997 (Box 18)
  - Mr. Universe and Other Plays, setting manuscript and page proofs, 1998 (Box 18)
  - Comfort and Joy, typescript with editing marks, 1995-1998 (Box 18)
  - Mr. Universe and Other Plays, setting manuscript and page proofs, 1998 (cont.) (Box 19)
  - Comfort and Joy manuscript, 1997 (Box 19)
  - Boulevard typescript with editing marks, undated (Box 19)
  - Boulevard typescript with publisher's editing marks (Box 20)
  - Kirith Kirin typescript with editing marks, 1999 (Box 20)
  - Boulevard typescript with comments by Elisabeth Lewis Corley, 2000 (Box 20)
  - Getting the News typescript with editing marks (Box 21)
  - Kirith Kirin typescript and page proofs with editing marks, 1999-2000 (Box 21)
  - Into Greenwood typescripts (2 versions), one with editing marks (Box 21)
  - The Ordinary (Box 22)
    Printout of pages written Summer 1999 prior to rewrite, Summer 2000.
  - Into Greenwood typescript, 2000 (Box 22)
  - Reason to Live typescript (Box 22)
  - Kirith Kirin cover (Box 22)
  - My Drowning, setting manuscript and page proofs, 1996-1997 (Box 22)
  - In Berlin script (2 copies), one with editing marks, 1998, 2000 (Box 22)
  - Boulevard (Box 22)
    Version printed April 1, 2000 before rewrites.
  - Thoroughly script, undated (Box 21)
    Early draft of play later retitled Free Market.
  - Composition book with pages inserted: Rewrite of Kirith Kirin, Feb. 1998 (Box 23)
  - Thoroughly script (Box 23)
  - Comfort and Joy, setting manuscript and page proofs, with editing marks, 1999-2000 (Box 23)
  - The Ordinary typescript (Box 23)
- Accessions (2015-0153) and (2016-0001)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use copies must be made in advance of a researcher's visit. Contact Research Services to request the production of access or listening copies. This restriction applies to materials in Box 30.
  - Drafts of Writings, 1980s-2010s
    - The Sanguine, undated (Box 25)
      typescripts; appeared in Asimov's
    - Wendy, 2006 and undated (Box 25)
      Science fiction story killed by Asimov. Includes galleys, Asimov's Forum thread about the incident. Story published in Subterranean.
    - Getting the News, undated (Box 25)
      Asimov's edited copy
    - Perfect Pilgrim, 2002 and undated (Box 25)
      Progress printings and Asimov's galleys
    - 120 Hours of Sodom, undated (Box 25)
      Drafts and Asimov's galleys
    - Georgia: A Twisted Road, 2003 (Box 25)
      Page proofs with edits
    - Stanley Karenina, 2004 (Box 25)
      Page proofs
    - On High, undated (Box 25)
      Working manuscript
    - Surely Some Revelation is at Hand, undated (Box 25)
    - Never Fallen, undated (Box 25)
    - The Physical Universe can be Transcended, undated (Box 25)
      Typescript
    - A Mother of Refugees, undated (Box 25)
    - Fish Lady, 1978 (Box 25)
    - Perfect Fit, undated (Box 25)
    - Dungeon Master, undated (Box 25)
    - The Existentialists, 1983 (Box 25)
      Photocopy of script
    - Fascination, undated (Box 25)
      Script, draft, etc.
    - In Berlin, undated (Box 25)
      Script, draft
    - Second Hand in Motion, undated (Box 25)
      Script
    - Kirith Kirin, 1999 (Box 25)
      Prep copy for ebook
    - 99 Uses for a Naked Man, 2007 and undated (Box 25)
      Script, drafts
    - Winter Birds, 2002; 2 folders (Box 25)
      Typescript, working manuscript draft
    - Comfort and Joy, 1992; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Last Green Tree, 2005 - 2006 and undated; 5 folders (Box 25)
      Three different versions of Last Green Tree. The first folder is the Fist Printed Copy. The First Draft - Editor's Copy consists of the next 2 folders. The last 2 folders are the Copy Editor's Manuscript.
    - Forgiveness, 2004 and undated; 4 folders (Box 26)
      Contains complete manuscript folder, Early partial manuscript folder, Bound copy with draft and cover proof page, and a partial manuscript folder (2004)
    - A Bird of Prey, 2006 (Box 26)
      Scripts
    - How I Shed my Skin, 2014 and undated; 6 folders (Box 26)
      Draft titles before final title include Good White People/Darkness and White. First two folders are typescript, followed by research materials (2014). The next two folders are typescript and typescript with edits. The final folder is a draft with edits for Darkness and White.
    - Unbending Eye, undated; 2 folders (Box 26)
      First folder is a working manuscript. Second folder is a manuscript notebook draft.
    - Turtle Run, 2001 (Box 26)
      Incomplete novel, typescript
    - Mrs. Delaney's Boarding House, undated; 2 folders (Box 26)
      Bound draft
    - Boulevard, 1982 and undated; 2 folders (Box 26)
      Manuscript excerpt folder (1982), and typescript folder (undated)
    - The Ordinary, 2003 and undated; 9 folders (Box 27)
      First two folders are Editor's Copy. Following three folders are Progress Print, probably the first complete manuscript. Next two folders are Progress Print, undated but smaller type indicates it is late in the book. A single folder is Early partial mansuscript. The last folder is Editor's Notes (2203).
    - Leap Project - Alliance, 2003-2004 and undated (Box 27)
      Includes music, notes, correspondence
    - Little Agnes, undated (Box 27)
      Incomplete Screenplay, collaboration with Madeleine St.Roman.
    - Dreamboy, 1998 and 2001; 2 folders (Box 27)
      Adaptations by Eric Rosen (1998) and James Bolten (2001). Both are drafts, James Bolten script based on Jim Grimsley's novel.
  - Bound galleys and published copies, various translations, of Grimsley's novels, 1990s-2010s (Box 24)
  - Published copies of anthologies containing Grimsley's writings, including speculative fiction, gay fiction, and Southern fiction genres, 1990s-2010s (Box 24)
  - Reviews, 2004-2006 and undated (Box 27)
  - Free Market, 2001 (Box 27)
    Reviews
  - Press/Coverage of Jim Grimsley, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Publications - Nonfiction serials, 1990s-2000s (Box 27)
  - Publications - Fiction serials, 1998-2003 (Box 27)
  - General Correspondence, 2001-2010; 6 folders (Box 28)
    5 folders are 2001-2009, last folder is 2009-2010.
  - Greeting cards, undated (Box 28)
  - Biz Kids board materials, 2000s (Box 28)
  - A Bird of Prey audiovisual, including Biz Kids recordings, undated; 3 items 2 cassettes and 1 CD (Box 30, Audio-cassette RL-00483-CS-0001, Audio-cassette RL-00483-CS-0002, Audio-cd RL-00483-OP-0001)
  - Game module for Neverwinken Nights, 2008 and undated (Box 28)
    Planning notes, working notes, notebook
  - 2 Notebooks with drafts of stories, 1974-1975 (Box 28)
  - Notebooks, diaries, some drafts, 1990s (Box 28)
  - Yearbooks, 1973 and 1994 (Box 28)
  - Convention materials, 2000s; 4 folders (Box 29)
  - Resume materials, 1990s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Emory University, 1998-2008 (Box 29)
    Correspondence, student work, other university business
  - Anthologies, 1995-2004 (Box 29)
    Correspondence
  - Peter Hagan, 1990-2005 (Box 29)
    Correspondence, contracts
  - Medical Systems Development Corp (MSDC), 1990 (Box 29)
    Jim Grimsley's invoices
  - Celeste Miller and Company, 1980's-1990's (Box 29)
    Correspondence, board materials
  - Algonquin, 1985-2003 (Box 29)
    Correspondence, royalties
  - PEN American Center, 1995-2003 (Box 29)
    Correspondence, membership
  - Royalty Statements, 1994-2010 (Box 29)
  - Contracts/Drafts, 1985 (Box 29)
    Agreement with Henry
  - ROOB, 2011-2002 (Box 29)
  - 7 Stages, 1999 and undated (Box 29)
    Correspondence, business materials
  - Tor Books, 2000s (Box 29)
    Correspondence, style sheets, proofs, edits
  - Playwriting classes by Jim Grimsley, 1980s-1990s (Box 29)
  - Lila Wallace, 1998 (Box 29)
    Reader's Digest Fund
  - Yaddo, 1986-1993 and undated (Box 29)
  - ACT SF, undated (Box 29)
    'A Bird of Prey' photographs
  - Handwritten Journal Pages from O'Neill Theater Center, 2002 (Box 29)
  - ACME Theater, 1982-1985 and undated (Box 29)
    Contracts, lease,, drafts
  - A Few Good Men/ You Never Know, undated (Audio-phonodisc RL-00483-PD-0001, Box 30)
    Removed from the ACME Theater folder.
  - Speeches, undated (Box 29)
    Drafts
  - About Face Theater, 2000-2003 (Box 29)
    Includes material re: Fascination
  - Book Beat episode 4, 2004 (Video-cassette RL-00483-VHS-0001, Box 30)
- Accession (2019-0050)
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use copies must be made in advance of a researcher's visit. Contact Research Services to request the production of access or listening copies. This restriction applies to materials in Box 31.
  - Agreements, 2001-2017 (Box 31)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 31)
  - Bookmarks, 1995-2000 (Box 31)
  - Emory University Selected Academic Highlights, 2002-2004 (Box 31)
  - Loose Canons, 1999-2008; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Photographs, 1999 and undated (Box 31)
  - Report of activities, 1999-2000 (Box 31)
  - Schedules, 2003-2017 (Box 31)
  - Speeches and interviews, 2003 and undated (Box 31)
  - Book reviews, 1994-2000; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Clippings, 1986-2016 (Box 31)
  - Course evaluations, 2002, 2004 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2018; 5 folders (Box 31)
  - Notecards, 2000-2018; 4 folders (Box 31)
  - New Jerusalem, City and Park, undated (Box 31)
  - Progressive Story, undated (Box 31)
    By Grimsley?
  - The Sanguine edited draft, undated (Box 31)
  - The Existentialists, 1983 (Box 31)
  - Winter Birds, 1984-1991; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Trigger Warnings, 2016 (Box 31)
  - Darkness and White, undated (Box 31)
  - Good White People page proofs, 2014; 4 folders (Box 31)
  - He's Right Here, He Says page proofs, 2016 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Writings by others, Basco, 1977 (Box 31)
  - Writings by others: Gunderson, 2003 (Box 31)
  - Writings by others: Laney book, 2017 (Box 31)
  - Writings by others: Leiner, 2014 (Box 31)
  - Dream Boy Screen Captures, undated (Box 31, Cd RL00483-OP-0002)
  - Dream Boy locations, 2011 (Box 31)
  - Dream Boy: A Tribute to Jim Grimsley, 2010 (Box 32)
  - Events, 1995-2018 (Box 32)
  - Emory publications, 1999-2003 (Box 32)
  - Publications featuring Grimsley, 1999-2007 (Box 32)